Guide to the Texas railroad history collection, 1867-1935 MS 640
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Texas railroad history collection
1867-1935
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Baker & Botts
MS 640
.5 Linear Feet 1 box
Pamphlets and documents documenting the history of Texas railroad lines such as Houston & Texas Central Railroad Co., Texas & Pacific Railway Co., Texas & New Orleans Railroad Co., Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway Co.
Biographical / Historical
Texas railroads began in 1852 with the first tracks laid, and became more prevalent in the 1860s and 1870s.
Scope and Contents
Pamphlets and documents documenting the history of Texas railroad lines such as Houston & Texas Central Railroad Co., Texas & Pacific Railway Co., Texas & New Orleans Railroad Co., Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway Co.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were deaccessioned from the Baker Botts historical collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series: General history, Houston & Texas Central Railroad Co., Texas & Pacific Railway Co., Texas & New Orleans Railroad Co., Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway Co.
Index Terms
Subjects
Railroads
Document Types
pamphlets
Places
Texas
- Series I: General history
  - A History of the Texas Railroads and of Transportation Conditions under Spain and Mexico and the Republic and the State (Box 1)
  - Railroad Consolidation in Texas, 1891-1903 (Box 1)
- Series II: Houston and Texas Central Railroad Co.
  - HTCRC First Mortgage and Condition of the Company, 1867 (Box 1)
  - the First Mortgage Land Grant Sinking Fund Gold Bonds of the HTCRC with copies of its Charter, Forms of Bond & Trust Deeds, 1871-05-01 (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation of the HTCRC, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Deed of Sale: Charles Dillingham (Special Commissioner), Nelson S. Easton & James Rintoul (Trustees), the Farmers' Loan & Trust Co. (Trustee), Benjamin A. Shepherd (Surviving Trustee), and the HTCRC to Frederic P. Olcott, 1889-01 (Box 1)
  - HTCRC to the Farmer's Loan and Trust Co.; cut-off first mortgage (Box 1)
  - HTCRC to Metropolitan Trust Co. of the city of New York; general mortgage, 1890-04-01 (Box 1)
  - HTCRC to the Farmer's Loan and Trust Co.; consolidated mortgage, 1890-04-01 (Box 1)
  - HTCRC to Central Trust Co. of New York; first mortgage, 1890-04-01 (Box 1)
  - HTCRC to Central Trust Co. of New York, 1890-05-01 (Box 1)
  - Petitions, Orders, Decrees, etc. in Consolidated Cause No. 198 in equity in Galveston; Nelson S. Easton et. als., trustees vs. HTCRC, et al, defendants (Box 1)
  - Deed: Alfred Abeel, master commissioner, to Wilbur F. Boyle, 1898-06 (Box 1)
- Series III: Texas & Pacific Railway Co.
  - Charter and other legislation relating to TPRC (Box 1)
  - TPRC Charter and Mortgages, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Legal Considerations affecting Texas Pacific Land Grant, 1871-03-03 (Box 1)
- Series IV: Texas & New Orleans Railroad Co.
  - Charter of TNORC, 1935-04-30 (Box 1)
  - Tracking Agreement: Yazoo & Mississippi Valley Railroad Co. et al. with TNORC et al., 1933-05-08 (Box 1)
  - Deed: Iberia and Vermilion Railroad Co. to TNORC, 1934-06-30 (Box 1)
  - Deed: Lake Charles & Northern Railroad Co. to TNORC (Box 1)
  - Deed: Texas Midland Railroad to TNORC, 1934-06-30 (Box 1)
  - Deed: Franklin and Abbeville Railway Co., 1934-06-30 (Box 1)
  - Deed: Dayton-Goose Creek Railway Co. to TNORC, 1934-06-30 (Box 1)
  - Deed: Gulf & West Texas Railway Co. to TNORC, 1934-06-30 (Box 1)
  - Deed: Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway Co. to TNORC, 1930-06-30 (Box 1)
- Series V: Galveston, Harrisburg and San Antonio Railway Co.
  - Charter of GHSARC (numerous copies) (Box 1)
  - Indenture: Guaranty Trust Co. of New York and GHSARC releasing lands from lien of first mortgage, Eastern Division, and supplemental indentures, 1910-06-29 (Box 1)
  - Indenture: GSARC Eastern Division Second Mortgage appointing Guaranty Trust Co. of New York, substitute trustee, 1905-10-01 (Box 1)
  - Brief for Appellee: Horace B. Stevens et al., appelllants, vs. GHSARC, appellee (Box 1)
  - Release of Lien on Lands, Eastern Division, Second Mortgage: Guaranty Trust Co. of New York to GHSARC, 1910-06-24 (Box 1)
  - M&P extension, Second Mortgage: GHSARC to Frank Storrs & William P. Hillhouse, 1881-07-01 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws of GHSARC, 1929-01-29 (Box 1)
  - Mortgage securing Galveston-Victoria Division First Mortgage Gold Bonds: GHSARC to Guaranty Trust Co. of New York, trustee, 1910-1940 (Box 1)